Guide to the Henry T. Bernstein on Environmental History Collection, 1965-1989 AIS.1994.12
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Henry T. Bernstein Collection on Environmental History
1965-1989
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bernstein, Henry T.
AIS.1994.12
28.13 Linear Feet (18 boxes)
Henry T. Bernstein, a professor of environmental history in London, England, assembled this collection of materials to document the various social, governmental, and economic programs and issues surrounding the burgeoning environmental movement of the 1960s and 1970s. The collection contains brochures, reports, newspaper clippings, event announcements, postcards, notes, correspondence, and publications that describe the current state of environmental awareness and environmental issues across Europe. The materials mainly document Great Britain, but they are also involved with environmental issues in continental Europe and the United States, and are in English, German, French, Italian, and Spanish.
Biography
As an environmental historian, Henry T. Bernstein, originally a Californian, specialized in research on forests and shipbuilding in the Indus-Ganges basin. He was one of the first academics in Great Britain to develop an interest in and teach a course on twentieth century British environmental history. As an academic discipline, environmental history draws upon the social sciences, the natural sciences, and the humanities - these varying disciplines are reflected in his collection of environmental materials.
Scope and Content Notes
The collection contains materials detailing environmental history in Europe and the United States, with a specific emphasis on Great Britain, from approximately 1965 to the early 1980s. It deals with several overarching themes, such as the different types of environments, the changes occurring to those environments, and the actions taken by government, voluntary organizations, individuals, and others in order to retard or reverse environmental degradation. The collection also includes reports and publications regarding environmental policy and political issues which are not widely available in the United States. Bernstein's notes, which can be found throughout the collection, may have been used for instruction in his environmental history classes at St. Mary's College in London. The documents occur in several different forms, such as brochures, reports, newspaper clippings, event announcements, postcards, notes, correspondence, and publications, and in several different languages, such as German, French, Italian, and Spanish. If undated, folders include documents covering much of the entire date range of the collection.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Henry T. Bernstein, October 1993.
Previous Citation
Henry T. Bernstein Collection on Environmental History, 1965-1989, AIS.1994.12, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Urban policy -- England -- London; Regional planning -- England -- London Metropolitan Area; City planning -- England -- London; Transportation -- Environmental aspects -- England; Environment; Housing -- Environmental aspects -- England; Land use -- England; Environmental management -- International cooperation; Environmental policy -- International cooperation; Environmental quality; Environmental education; Bernstein, Henry T.
- International Conferences and Environmental Cooperation, I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains the reports, conference proceedings, publications, and articles of several European and International conferences concerning the environment in the 1970s-1980s. Also included are documents related to the United Nations and other international groups that considered environmental issues during the 1970s. Especially prominent in this series are the Council of Europe and the United Nations (particularly their conference on the environment in Stockholm in 1972).
  - European National Park Brochures, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - European Association for Organic Agriculture and Health, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Commission Des Communautes Europeennes (Commission of the European Communities), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Official Journal of the European Communities, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Environmental Issues, Reports submitted to European Environmental Conference (Box 1, Folder 5-10)
  - United Nations Publications, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Forms, United Nation Information Requests (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United Nations Information (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Council of Europe Publications and Reports, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 14-17)
  - Council of Europe Official Documents, Nature in Focus (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Council of Europe (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - International Environmental Relations (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - European Ministerial Conference on the Environment, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Management of the Environment in Tomorrow's Europe (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - European Environmental Policy (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - State of the Environment, CEC (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - International Conference on the Environment, Papers (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Papers, theme 1-6 (Box 2, Folder 6-11)
  - Article, Environment in Europe (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ambiente / Environment (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Cities (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Environment/City and Suburbs (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - United Nations Conference, Stockholm, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Stockholm Articles, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 18-21)
  - Stockholm Environs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Stockholm Booklet and Programs, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - United Nations and the Human Environment (Box 3, Folder 3-11)
  - London's Environment, Report for Stockholm, June 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Human Environs (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Economic Commission, Environmental Committee (Stockholm), 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14-15)
- Environment in specific countries (excluding England), II.
  This series contains information related to environmental issues in European countries, in the United States, and elsewhere in the world. These documents are in the form of publications, brochures, newspaper clippings, correspondence, reports, and essays. This material is often in languages other than English, and includes documentation from the mid-1960s through the late 1970s. Finally, the materials in this series are grouped by country in the following order: Germany, France, Italy, Scotland, miscellaneous nations, and lastly the United States.
  - Germany, 1966-? (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
  - German Correspondence and Notes (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - West Germany Environs, Durcksache! (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - The Rhine, publications in German (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Maps (German) (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - L'Express Magazine (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - French Publications (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - French Publications (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Paris, Modern Developments, Grands Trauaux (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Paris (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - SNCF Publication, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Solar Power, France (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Motor Exhaust, France (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - France (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Water Quality and Quantity, France (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chantiers et Projets de L'environnement (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Languedoc Rousillion Region (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Venice (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Consiglio Nazionale delle Richerche, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - First Report on the Italian Environment (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Inquinamento, no. 5-10, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Mediterranean Coast (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Edinburgh (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - New Towns, Scotland, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scotland Development (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scotland (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Annual Report for the Registrar of Scotland, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Scottish Home and Health Department Reports, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cadiz Oil Spill/Oil on Coasts (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Environs by Country (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Sweden (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - International Environs (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Environment by Country - USSR and Norway (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chapter V: Leman and the Rhine (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Project Lack Geneva (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Switzerland/Lake Geneva (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - The Environment in Israel, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - International Coastal Issues (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Marine Pollution/Resources (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - International Coastal Issues, Cote D'Azur (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - New York City (NYC) Drafts (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - NYC Air Pollution (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - NYC Water (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chapter IV: NYC and the World (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - NYC Northeast Power Failure and Urban Crisis (Chapter I-II) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - NYC, 1945-1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Air, California (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Preservation, United States (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - United States, Nuclear power (Box 6, Folder 10)
- England's Environmental Issues, III.
  This series includes information specifically related to England in the 1960s and 1970s. Subjects include: transportation, various types of pollution, the preservation of the countryside or natural areas, city living, power and energy, water conservation, the preservation of historic buildings, safety, and the actions taken concerning environment. The materials are generally in the form of brochures, government publications, newspaper clippings, event announcements, Bernstein's notes, and correspondence.
  - Tower Hamlets - Borough Plan Topics:, Oct.-Nov. 1976, Jan. 1977 (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
  - Tower Hamlets - Factories and Warehouses Available, Feb. 1977 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Cities/Housing (Box 6, Folder 15-18)
  - Housing and Redevelopment (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - New Towns (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Lewisham Central Area Booklet (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Milton Keynes, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Low-rise, Lillingston Gardens, 1961-1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - High Rises, "Green Giant" (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Villages (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Selburne Documentation (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Planning and Development Control (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Derelict Land (Chapter 11, lithosphere and atmosphere) (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Industrial Zones (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - English Cities - Bibliography (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Transport (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Transportation Reports, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Car Safety (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Electric Car (Box 7, Folder 14-17)
  - Car Impact and Solutions (Box 7, Folder 18-19)
  - Cars (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Blackheath and Motorway - My Defense (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Railway, British Rail (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Railways, Channel Tunnel (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - Railway Documentation (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Bicycle by Rail (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Bicycle Ban (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
  - Gatwick Airport (Box 8, Folder 11-12)
  - Nuclear Energy (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
  - Windmills - Wind power (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Electricity/Power and the Environment (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Mineral Resources (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - Energy Alternatives, Fossil Fuel (oil, coal, gas) (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Soil (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Countryside Magazines (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Countryside Protection, Sport/Hunting (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Countryside, Nature and Leisure (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Countryside, Forests and Trees (Box 9, Folder 5-6)
  - Countryside, Inter/Postwar Bibliography (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Countryside/Farms (Box 9, Folder 8-9)
  - Heavy Horse v. Tractor (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Mountains (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Nature Reserves (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Nature Conservancy (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - National Parks (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Sheffield, 1949, 1965, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
  - Sheffield, YHA (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Pennine Way (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Peak District National Park (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - National Society for Clean Air (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Air Pollution and Control (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Atmosphere, climate, and space (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Canals Documentation (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Water Supply (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Water Resources and Pollution (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - Marine Pollution (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Water Pollution, Great Britain (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Birds and Oil Pollution (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Wildlife and Habitat Protection (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Sewage, Water-borne Waste (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Waste Documentation (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Solid Waste (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Side Effects and Pollution (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Preservation of Ancient Monuments/Historic Buildings (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Stonehenge Documentation (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bath (City) Documentation (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
  - Bloomsbury and the Museum/British Library (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Technosphere (Man and Machine) (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Biosphere/Environmental Dangers/Accidents (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Safety Precautions - Hazards and Accidents (Box 11, Folder 9-12)
  - TV and Violence (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - TV and Violence (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Biocides (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Intensive Beef Fattening (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Dairy Farming (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Food (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Noise Publications (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Noise and Aircraft, Concorde and London (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Noise Documentation (Box 12, Folder 8-10)
  - Actions/Movements (Box 12, Folder 11-16)
  - Human Reactions (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Human and Social Aspects and Environs Change (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Reactions and Counter-reaction (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Notes, Parliamentary Papers (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Environmental Magazines (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Indicators (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Objection Groups against Ringwall (INNE) Details (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Friends of the Earth (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Center for Environmental Studies (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Resolve, 1920 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - CPRE Sussex (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Conservation Society - Town/Country Planning (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Parliamentary Papers (Box 13, Folder 9-10)
- London, IV.
  This material deals specifically with the environmental issues in the city of London. It is dated mainly in the 1960s and 1970s. The form of the documents includes brochures, city planning reports, publications, newspaper clippings, correspondence, etc.
  - London Borough Information - Greenwich (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - St. Katherine's (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - St. Paul's (Box 13, Folder 13-14)
  - Mansion House (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Barbican (Box 13, Folder 16-17)
  - Covent Garden (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Tower of London Publications (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Tower of London, School Trip (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Reconstruction in the City of London (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Invisible London (Box 14, Folder 4-5)
  - London Clippings (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - London: People and Dwellings (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - London "City" Skyline (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Tall Buildings, London (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Port of London, Thames Pollution Control (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
  - Thames Riverway (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - City of London, Misc. Publications (Box 14, Folder 13-14)
  - Greater London Council (GLC) (Box 14, Folder 15-18)
  - Research Bibliography (Box 14, Folder 19-20)
  - Research Guides (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Greater London Development Plan (GLDP), V.
  This series contains the papers of the proceedings of the Greater London Development Plan (GLDP) Inquiry. The papers concern various areas of environmental concern in London, such as housing, pollution, and transportation. Box 15, folders 1 and 2 include information about the conference and give descriptions of the labeling schema used to describe these documents. The GLDP was in session between 1970 and 1973.
  - GLDP Inquiry, Guide to the GLDP Papers (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - GLDP Inquiries, Lists 1-48 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - GLDP Inquiry B (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
  - GLDP Inquiry E11-E12 (Box 15, Folder 5-11)
  - GLDP Inquiry E12- E111 (Box 16, Folder 1-11)
  - GLDP Inquiry S11 (Box 16, Folder 12-15)
  - GLDP Inquiry S12 (Box 17, Folder 1-12)
  - GLDP Inquiry S13-S111 (Box 18, Folder 1-4)
  - GLDP Inquiry XE, XS, XP, XO (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - GLDP Inquiries Y (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - GLDP Inquiry ZE, ZO, ZS, ZP (Box 18, Folder 7-8)
  - GLDP Inquiry P11-P19, P27, P110-111 (Box 18, Folder 9-10)
  - GLDP Inquiries O11-O19, O110-O111, O27 (Box 18, Folder 11-13)